Hey there, Welcome back to this
ASP.NET Core videos series,
My name is Jeff Fritz, I'm Jon Galloway.
And you know what Jon, we've spent
lot of time writing code,
writing some HTML in to Razor templates,
or Razor pages,
and that's lot of code that I've to write.
What if I want to do, re-use some of that?
Yeah, you know, let me tell you
recently I ran into this,
where I was working on
the .NET foundation website. Oh! OK.
And Index field for home page,
there's a lot information in there.
There's all kinds of stuff
and some parts of it are things
like a little News view.
You know, a little list of recent blogs posts.
And there's some frustrating things
with this. One is, My view is huge.
Times are I'm scrolling, scrolling
scrolling to get to it. I don't like that.
Another prob-- and I can break it
apart with partials,
but it just kind of moves a problem,
It doesn't really fix things.
Another thing is, I want to componentize,
so I can reuse like you said
and I also don't want my controllers
or my page code-behinds to have to return
really complex models
I've all kind of-- here is my list in the
here is my list of bloggers, here is my--
and then if I want to
implement it somewhere else on this site.
It kind of do that all over again. Yes.
That's difficult. Yeah--
Ok, so what's the solution for that?
Well, so we talked about this
and I thought it was find kind of
running through the list with a--
you know, we're talking about
like well we could do, partial as we could do--
you know back we-- there is a child actions
which are available
on child actions work for--
MVC and with a child action you can
put inside a controller
you can say, this is just
you know for a partial view
that's going to be return by
this controller.
But the problem there it's still
tied directly to controller.
Right. And then you mention tag helpers,
and tag helpers is a
is a nice solution, I can-- a tag helper can
I can create a nice little markup
and I can say, write this thing out.
The problem kind of a--
the tag helper is I loose a Razor formatting.
Okay, get to wait all your code,
all your formatting in C#. Yeah.
A tag helper is written in C#,
and so I am formatting strings into HTML.
That's not beautiful! No.
So the solution here is view component.
OK. A view component is really cool,
because it allows me to
make a small little component.
It's stand alone.
It doesn't do the whole model binding
kind of thing that I would use in.
in pages or MVC.
But it is something
I can just drop into any view
it works all by itself and the nice thing
with it is, there's a simple class
and it has all the thing, all dependency
injection has all my services available.
And then it's all got an
associated razor template.
Very cool! So I get the
benefits of working in razor?
I get you know, nice I can write
nice component, nice code in a class.
Yep, drop it in where ever.
Cool! Lets take a look. Yeah!
So here let me show an example
This is actually the page
I was talking about,
so this is an example homepage.
I think of your home page your website
right, there is a tons of different stuff.
And just I am scrolling through
here is the list of news on the left,
list of the events on the right.
So there's-- there some dropping things
If I look down at the bottom here
again, I have got a list of recent posts.
These are things that you know,
you may consider some other things like
and on the doc's which
are pretty good for this here.
They list some things like you may
have something like a Tag cloud
or Shopping cart something where you know,
you want to drop it into
a page and it's not just
if its just a chunk of mark up
I would use just a PowerShell.
Sure, but if it's something
where if you've actually got some--
something to populate here like
a Shopping cart list,
I really do think to make since to have
you know some code behind for it.
You-- you need that
server side code to interact.
Exactly-- Exactly! OK. So, what I'm
going to be talking through here I--
I refer you to the doc's if you
go to view components
is information about what a
view component is and it talk's you through
building a view component
and there is actually a
whole walkthrough down at the end,
Creating a simple view component.
So, I've actually got that running
quickly and let's take a look at
what the code-- you know, how that code looks.
So here we've got actually
here's this is a standard view,
down at the bottom,
we've got this await InvokeAsync
and it's a priority list, it says
Component InvokeAsync.
So, it's pulling in this view Component
that way.
If we look at how that view Component is
defined, we've here-- it's a
passed in here from view Component,
and then it just has a-- here's it's got a
GetItemsAsync. So, really that's-- there's
not a lot of coder here. What's nice is,
a table too, it can use Dependency injections
here, they're using a
data context, OK, I'm just injecting it there,
you can also inject other services etc.
Sure, And so all this is
doing is returning a list.
So this is async so it's  returning
a list of to do items as a task.
Then in the view for that
its just binding to it
so this is a very simple binding
here we got an IEnumerable
and we are just binding
to that a IEnumerable list.
And there is some convention to this
this is called default.cshtml.
And the kind of naming convention
here is you have components
priority list is the its a priority list
few component
and then its called Default.cshtml.
So this is very similar to have
we have to views folder above
Exactly and this is the views for
a component being hosted inside of
a to do control.
Yes and this sample shows multiple
four ways of hosting, so there actually
some different names on this
Oh but this one also is
the standard would be default cshtml
and you can put that either in shared
or in the view specific one
in the controller specific one ,
controller specific exactly.
So this way I can use
the same component change the
mark up slightly based on
my different controllers needs.
Exactly, so I could have a shared one that's
the standard one and then within
other controllers I can go and mark that up
a bit. Terrific. So this really
is pretty straight forward, now because
this is not depending on anything
else, in-order to display
I drop it into any razor view.
So the kind of simple way to inject this,
simple meaning the default
standard way is, I'm doing
Component.InvokeAsync
and then since I don't have model binding
I'm actually passing in parameters here.
Sure. So, I'm saying this is you know
the priority to take and this is whether
show if they are done or not. Okay.
Because this is for a To-Do-List.
This is okay, but I actually prefer
to share this using a Taghelper,
this is pretty slick, because
Taghelpers clean-up our gray razor-
mark-up. They do, right. Here
they've actually got
If I do vc: it automatically-- like
view components just automatically
become Taghelpers. OK, so it's
just built-in so, just by creating
priority-list, vc priority list
automatically works and on my
properties here also
automatically bound for me.
So we are getting the hyphen's between
the names of our attributes
and the name of
our Taghelper because that's where the
boundary is between the
capitalized word in the name. Exactly.
Yeah, so it does that conversion for me.
So that's pretty cool,
let me show you an example then
kind of to run back to
how I uses this in mine, so
I had some mark up for to like this,
this is just kind of
staging mark up, right, but so
why I am showing this news items
and this is, it's using boot strap, I'm
using Holder.js to
share different kind of
mark-up like thumbnail for them you know
so with bootstrap
I've got media-heading, media-body
pull-left all that kind of stuff. Oh yeah!
So I would now want to generate this
all in C# but, there is actually some of
reasonable manual code.
There is pulling,
this is actually pulling
it from IIS feeds and stuff.
So here I've got a NewsFeedService
and my NewsFeedService is it's-- it's
running this kind of background task,
it's actually using a Syndication.
These Syndication feed
which just was made
available in-- in .NET standard
too recently which is very cool.
So it's kind of running this
and this is a service that I've got.
So then I've-- I've got in my component,
I'm able to inject that.
So I inject my service
you know, using constructive injection
so I said that
newsService there and then
I just call my InvokeAsync.
This one is simpler than that
other one that you
todo list we are showing,
it's not hitting
your database or whatever the services
doing the-- the hard work here.
So which just you know, you know
getting the feed, the feed is cash
behind the scenes and the service
and it's grabbing a quantity
and that quantity
is been passed in here
actually it's an input parameter.
Exactly! so I can say this is how
many news items I want to show.
And then I can go over
and here is my actual
this is how I converted it into razor.
So I just binding
to IEnumerable news items
and then I'm just using my standard razor
you know I'm doing the few things
items can take just like for instance
there is multiple URIs
associated with the newsfeed,
because there is also an RSS feed
for comments and stuff like that.
So I'm garbing the first and then here
on the description I'm taking
the first 50 characters.
Right, so basically that's all that
involved in setting that up.
So,this is the razor template
that your component is
view is rendering with. Exactly!
ok and so then that
just to kind of show whether
that goes that is in, let me see
NewsView right there,
it's a Default.cshtml, ok.
So that's it.
So really pretty straight forward,
it solves a problem that
when you run into it.
Yes I mean, I wish I can packages up.
I don't want to have to
if you find yourself
from a page or controller
returning a very complex model
that has here is a list of these
and here is list of those and all that.
That's kind of sign that you may
want to move that into a component
and then if you got re-usable code
that you just want to reuse to your side.
Yeah! So this is in really a construct,
this is in the view structure
like Tag Helpers
they would want to bundle up
into a NuGet package and deploy
Because of I got that razor template
that I need to deploy
appropriately inside my application.
Exactly, Yeah I think this is something
where it's more kind of
application specific,
there may be some you know
super black belt layer
doing some kind of path
provided bla-bla-bla to inject that
I think the standard case is just
go through cleanup my markup and take
common things I'm going
to use though my site,
put the razor template there,
put my one class,
right my one simple class
and then just reuse from
my site then. Terrific!
Alright, so that's about it.
Thank you for joining us
and we hope you join us
for the next video on ASP.NET Core.