Hey welcome back to this
video series about ASP.NET core.
My name is Jeff Fritz
and I'm John Galloway
and John you know what!
both of Americans
and although you tried to be a Canadian,
I tried to be a Canadian earlier failed.
But I barely speak English well, yeah.
and I learn another language
and I know a lot of the folks out there
I'm sure you don't speak
English as your first language
how do I go about
localizing and making sure that
our ASP.NET core web applications work
better for those folks
who aren't American and aren't English.
You know that's a
great question and it's one that
I've been doing ASP.NET presentations
for a while and it's one that I've
got over the years for previous
versions of ASP.NET and I never had a
good answer and people would say like
hello you're in Germany, you're speaking
to me about ASP.NET
and my sites don't work in German.
You know I'm going to say
yeah sorry about that.
Fortunately with ASP.NET core we've got
a good solution for that they've
actually thought through this
and I'm really pretty happy with
the level of support for
globalization and localization.
Here in the docs, the globalization,
localization in ASP.NET Core doc
is there's a lot information here,
another thing that I love is just
looking at the name of contributors.
For instance Nadeem and Hisham
both folks that are not from the US
and our experts in localization
and have contributed code
and documentation to this.
So it's exciting to see
the global community
contributing to our
globalization localization efforts.
Awesome! first term as far as
globalization
and localization definitions.
So globalization is the process of
making my application able to
speak many languages ok and then
localization is the step of actually
saying great now let's target it for a
a specific culture or language, right!
ok. So globalization is opening it up
and then localization is focusing it to
a list of supported languages alright.
Right, so there's a lot of
different things in here.
There's information about
how to make my content localizable.
The main things that you're going to see
is your code behind and your razor right
those are your two
kind of main places. OK.
So we'll take a quick look at this
this is like I said
this is a long document
and there are some complexities
to localizing your applications
and so I refer you to the
docs to really dig into this.
But for the time we have to look at
this I'm going to show you first of all
here is a localization sample.
This is prepared, this is
actually in that doc
it goes through and it talk to you
through this exact demo here ok.
So with some things that are set up here,
first of all in my services so I'm
running the app right now so I've got a
smaller screen available. But in my
services we actually as part of
configuring services built into that is
the ability to say things like here
are my SupportedCultures right.
So I can go through
and I can say here are the
SupportedCultures that my application
has so this is the after I've globalized
it this is these are the languages I've
localized for okay so I can go through
and set both SupportedCultures
and I can also go in and say
set a DefaultRequestCulture okay.
So if the browser does not
present a culture it doesn't
say the local languages then this is
I can go through here and I can specify
that and I could even for all these
things because they're in code I can go
through and run my own custom logic
maybe even hit a database. Hmm okay.
So that's that part there.
Let's take a look at this this app actually,
so this is you know
this is an example application
you'll see down in the footer it says
language is English and if I drop this
down now I'm in French right and so
portions of this have been localized
this is using the resources.
Ok, take a look in a second but this is
showing kind of where this comes from.
I my French is not so good.
So you know but we can look around
throughout the site and we see we can
see them some things in here.
So for instance let's see if we've got
our contact page and yes our contact
page is localized right. So we can
actually take a look at how these
resources are set up, one other thing
actually Before we jump into that I want
to point out just a small funny thing.
I wanted to show this off and here they've
built in this little drop down for
English and French right that's built
into the sample. Into the sample.
That's not built into ASP.NET Core,
that's not a standard feature. No!
And so I didn't realize that was there.
Fortunately for you I'm going to show
you something that you can use. So this
is an example, this is an extension where
I can go in and change
my language, my culture
as I'm sending it back to the browser.
So I can actually in here if I set this to
French you can use this as
your testing your applications this is a
a culture switcher right and so you can
go through and do that
in your apps as well.
So that will what that culture
switcher does is it effectively changes
the browser to send that header that
says accept the french language
information. Exactly! yep, so now let's
look at how those
resources are configured.
So these are actually the
standard kind of default way that
.NET does localization is using
resource files. So if I go into one of
these there's a these
are actually .resx files or XML
but there is an editor
thing for this that I can editor plugin
for Visual Studio it's built into the UI
right. Yep! so that's kind of the standard
way to do this. It is an extensible
system where I can kind of I can supply
those other ways but this is kind of
what the tooling is built in for this
and then when I look at how I light this
up in a view for instance,
we use this Localizer.
What's neat about this
Localizer is it actually is the key is
my DefaultCulture. So what I can
say here is if there's nothing
specified or if it's my local culture
I'm going to use homepage otherwise I'm
going to pull it in I'm going to use
that is the key to look up
what it should be. Alright!
That makes sense, if you've
used localization in the past it can be
frustrating to try and dig through
and understand you know it's hard to
read localized pages. Because the
localized pages themselves can be they
can be it's a bunch of keys, it's a bunch
of you know strange hard to read things
so for instance if we look at this now
here if we look at my contact page
you'll see that these localized strings
say things like Localizer phone, look
Localizer support. So it's actually
pretty readable right
and then if I want to look at well what is
the localized string for instance
support on my contact page. Now I go into
contact and I can see here support
and you know that's what it's
pulling in from that one right.
So it's actually just
showing that string there
but it's explaining that's
where it came from.
Now I'm seeing a hierarchy and it looks
like a naming convention
for these resource files.
Yeah! that's true.
So that's how they're being pulled
in based on you know exactly here's the
views and it actually maps Views -> Home
and then down here we've got the same
this is Views -> Home. Right.
So if i'm in my Home view,
my home index view page
yeah and i'm referencing the localizer
and i've specified the home page item
in the index were there,
it's going to reach
into the views -> home -> index resource
and look for that same home page item.
Oh there it is but halfway down
okay yep and so there we are this is the
Index.fr and then if i had others if
I had you know
Japanese index.jaa.resx. It's better.
Okay and you were making the point that
it uses my default language
as the Index for these keys
over here, that way if I'm not an
English speaker and I'm writing this
and perhaps, I'm French and I'm writing it
and I want to preferred
German translations
and whatnot, I can use my native language
as the keys to access
these. Exactly! Fanatstic!
and so then your view can be readable
by you know whatever your
local language is in that case exactly!
Okay, so that's really handy.
So that's kind of the mainthing
there's also of course, we're also seeing
things like here is my
for the controller
as well, right. So here I've got resources
for my HomeController and let's take
a look in my controllers up here
and we'll look in my HomeController
and so we've passed in
this IStringLocalizer.
Right and then we're able to
it's injected and it's just
ViewData message here normally I would
just set a string
instead I use localizer
and calling to that service
I've injected and then again that key.
So my controller the code is still
readable by me and my default language
in my local language right and then it's
actually just going to
localizer this at runtime.
So once again the localizer knows
that it's operating inside of
the HomeController class
exactly! We're going to find
the HomeController resource yep,
to inject from yeah I got it okay yeah.
So that's really all there is to it.
One other cool thing
I want to show you is
resx files are kind of a
Microsoft localization thing
and it works great for
some people, the tooling
is all there and all that. I've talked
to some people that do a good amount of
localization and PO files are kind of
standard outside of the
Microsoft Dev world. Ok.
PO files the format is pretty simple
and it can also be easy to
pass off to a localizer,
they can do the work they
know their PO files it's
easy to work with and then they
can kind of pass it back to you.
So do I have to convert
those PO files to resx!
No! so that's a cool thing.
So the orchard project or
Orchard Core, so if I lookup here.
Let's go to
orchardproject.net I believe,
so Orchard is a .NET powered CMS ok,
and orchard core
has support for PO file
localization. So this is actually
in the docs here if we go to you know the
docs.microsoft.com,looking in the
globalization, localization section.
They talk about PO files and recommend
using as Orchard core for that.
So here, you're seeing
here is a sample PO file
it can be a lot simpler
and lighter weight to use a PO file
I supposed to a resx file which you know
has a lot of XML to it right.
So that's kind of the standard for it,
for how it looks and then here
you'll see inside the application,
so here we are doing
services.AddPortableObjectLocalization.
So that's really that lights that up,
otherwise we just configure those
default and SupportedCultures
just like
we did before. Right, so that's
and then the final thing
I want to show you here is my PO file.
Okay, so you know to kind of circle way
back, we talked about
what globalization
and localization are. In the process of
internationalizing an application
globalizing is making
your application
ready to be localized. Localization is
where you actually drill down and you
say I support the following four
languages and you know here's how I turn
on the here's how I write those strings.
We looked at how you can use the
localizer both in views and in my code
and my controllers
or code-behind using
that localizer service
and then finally,
we looked at where I can get those
strings from and
we can pull them either
from a resx file and that's supported
in the Visual Studio tooling
and it's an XML file
if you prefer to use PO files
we looked at how Orchard Core
supports that and we showed a sample of
using that. That's terrific!
So I'll circle back finally to if you
want to dig deeper into this I highly
recommend the docs on this and the
sample file again these people
are worldwide experts on
on localization and ASP.NET
and they've been doing it
before ASP.NET Core with the thing.
These are the people you want to
learn from, terrific! Yeah so that's it,
that's our look at Globalization
and Localization in ASP.NET Core.
Thank you for joining us
and we hope you watch some more of
our videos on ASP NET Core.
Catch you later.