Hi! Welcome back to this video series
on ASP.NET Core.
I'm Jon Galloway and I'm Jeff Fritz.
So we're going to be talking here about
configuring and working
with multiple environments.
Yeah, we've-- we've kicked around this
notion of production and development.
It's funny ASP.NET Core actually knows
what these things mean and we can
light up different features
based on which environment
we're operating it.
You know that's-- that's
one of those things where
when you think back about it
we're always working with
like you said there's development
there's staging or test
and there's production and you know
and-- and it's nice to have the web framework
understand that and know about
that and work with me.
Absolutely, I like being able to
enable and disable features
based on where I am, great!
Let's take a look.
So here I am in Visual Studio.
I'm going to start up a new project
and I'll choose to build
a new ASP.NET Core Application.
I'm going to put it in my dev folder
and we will call this environment.
Now, I'm going to create an empty project
because I want to focus
on the different things
that are available in the environments.
So it's created very quickly for me
and I'll bring up my program cs to start.
And you could see here all that
we're doing right from the get-go is
create my default builder
use my startup class and build.
Well, that start up class has just a few
things configured in our first feature
that's only enabled in
development environment
is right here on line 23 to 26,
where it says if the
environment is development
then use the developer exception page.
And that's great for when I'm debugging
and I want to be able to see
the exact stack trace
of it what happened
inside of my application.
When I want to deploy this
to my production space I'd rather use
a more friendly error handler,
that shows some nice
information to my visitors.
So they don't get to see that
ugly stack trace.
I tell you Jon was the
scariest thing when I at an airport
and one of those display screens
showing the departure times
for all the flights
was showing the old ASP.NET error page.
Oh! The yellow screen of that,
the old yellow screen oh,
no you don't want to see that
anywhere but especially not at
the airport and not at the airport.
So this is a good comfort thing
to only show that
developer exception page
when you're in development mode.
You know, it improves confidence.
So this configure method runs
when I configure my pipeline
write my HTTP pipeline
on a normal application
and I have this one startup class.
And if I navigate to this right
and I'm just going to throw
an exception here right,
that was an error and I'm going to run this.
So when I run this now
from my command line
you'll see it's going to do the compile
and it's going to come back and say that it's
running in the development environment,
and it's listening on this
web address and port. OK.
Let me copy that and I'm going
to navigate there with my browser.
And write this is that-- that error message
that I was expecting to see right,
this is the developer exception page.
Because, you're in development
you want to say that
so we can fix it.
So I can fix that right. So my
hosting environment is development
and I get my
development feature enabled.
Now I can change that and I can turn on
a different environment by setting
an environment variable and infact
Visual Studio did that for me
when I Configured the application.
Check this out. I'm going to go to
Project, Properties and I will look at
Debug and right here
in the middle of my screen,
there we go. It sets up
an environment variable when I launch
from within Visual Studio that
says ASPNETCORE_ENVIRONMENT
is development. So, whenever I'm debugging
from Visual Studio, I'm going to get all
those development features
that I've Configured inside of
my application. But, I'm not running
from within Visual Studio, I'm running from
my command line. The next feature
that Visual Studio lit up for me is
inside of my properties of the Project
it generated a file called
launch settings and this is a bunch of
settings that are used when you're
launching your application to set the
various things that actually
we saw in a previous video
around how to host your application,
what is the application URL
that you're listening on and even some
environment variables right here.
So, we've got hard-coded into this-- into this
configuration that were in
development mode.
So, because I ran from the command line,
it actually ran this set
of configuration options
into my project,
so that I was listening on 63 for 39 and it
set my environment to development.
Nice! OK! So if I want that to not be set
by default from inside of this file I can
clear that out, I'll clear this and now
if I execute dotnet run, so I executed
dotnet run and you see it's now saying
the hosting environment is production.
So, when I don't specify an
ASPNETCORE_ENVIRONMENT,
it defaults to thinking it's
running in production, which means all
those places where we said,
if this is development
putting these extra features,
those things go away
and it'll behave more like a
production server, where we'll start
turning on some features
that make it a little bit more secure,
it hardens ASP.NET Core and makes it feel
more production ready.
So now let me go back to my website
and when I refresh,
I don't get my error. There was nothing
to return it through the error and infact
that error is here inside my log
but it didn't finish
and to prevent any of that information
from leaking outside my application,
it didn't return a things,
it made-- it kept the screen blank
nothing happened here. Great! So if
I did have an error check in there
I could go route appropriately to some
other location. So I'm pretty
professional-looking error page
absolute, that fits in with
the rest of my application
and isn't it a yellow screen
of doom like I saw at the airport, maybe
something like an animated gif
of a man with a shovel,
like a construction something
1996 website
called "John we want you back".
Alright, so that's how you can
Configure your web, how you can light up
that development feature but there's
also some other things we can do here
as we build our application to actually
pivot and bring in different features
and Configure for different environments.
So we know there's an
IsDevelopment method,
there's also IsProduction or IsStaging
and those tests to see if the
environment is named Production
or Staging? That kind of makes sense.
But this last one here
that I want to point out
IsEnvironment. This is the
interesting one because I can provide
my own string name for an environment
that I want to test against.
So Development, Production, Staging,
those might not be the terms
that you use with your organization.
You might use a different name like
Test or Integration, alright?
or write whatever your organization
uses, for your environment names
you can create
and put those same tests in here
to verify that you're operating in
that environment before you light up
different features. Now that's one thing
to pivot and put in if-statements
to verify and Configure things.
However you'd like,
but you can actually go even
a step further where
I have a Startup class here
I can actually change my
Configure Services, so that it triggers
a Configure Services that exists and is
written for my development environment
by calling it
Configure Services Development.
And because I've put the name
of my environment,
at the knee-- at the end
of that method name, it'll find this
and execute this, when it's in
development mode.
Now you'd probably going to want to have
a Configure Services method
hanging around also in case it can't
find an environment name that matches
one of your overrides that you have here.
You can use that same trick with the
Configure mode
with the Configure method,
I'm sorry, in order to provide a feature
that's specific to being in
that environment.
So, tell you what let me just
copy this and I'm going to go down here
and add another method
and this time I'll call it
Configure Development
and instead of configuring all that
other stuff in the pipeline
I'm actually just going to say
app.Run async context
right and that I will say
await context.Response
WriteAsync, Hello from Development
semicolon good, now let me
rerun that application.
So now it thinks I'm in production,
I'll refresh and I still get my blank page.
So now let's cancel this let me set
my ASPNETCORE ENVIRONMENT
to development,
and rerun the application,
and now it thinks I'm in the
development environment, so,
I'll go back, refresh and it says
Hello from Development. So I can embed
different configuration methods
that point to
and Configure my application
differently depending on which
environment I'm in. So those are options
that you can choose to use
as you're building out your application.
One last trick with that,
that I want to make sure
you see, I'm going to go back into my code
here and besides having a
Configure Development method
right, I'll get rid of that
I can actually have a different
Startup class sitting here as well.
So check this out, if I create public class
Startup Development right,
I need a Configure services
and a Configure method in there.
So I will just start off by
copying these, alright
and in this one I will do the exact same
app.Run async context
await context.Response
Write and this time we will say
Hello from Startup Development.
Alright. Sem it, it will finish it.
Now in order for me to be able to use
this Startup class and I have it
detecting use the Startup class
that I want based on the
environment name, I need to make a slight
change here from where
it says UseStartup
and specifies
a specific Startup class.
I need to tell it instead, what
assembly to go search for this Startup
class in and run the appropriate one.
So my assembly is called environments,
so I will just call it environments
and it will go find the
appropriate Startup class
for me to run. So I will cancel this
I'll dotnet run again, so it thinks I'm
running in the development environment
I'll refresh from over here and it says
Hello from StartupDevelopment.
so we written a little bit of code that is
able to interpret, what
environment we are on
use different features around the
Startup class as needed for those
different environments and trigger
different configurations as needed. Ok!
This is a great configuration
option for folks,
who have different needs
in different environments,
maybe you're in a
regulated environment and your
production space is
governed by HIPAA rules
and there's certain things that you
only want to light up in development.
That can never get into production, you
can do things around writing a start up
production class that excludes all of
those development things
that nobody can
change and you can make sure is the one
that runs every time when
you get into production.
I can see all kinds of users like you
showed the development exception page.
I may want to have some sample data
maybe when I'm running in development
mode I want to have a ton of data that's
going to because
I'm all on a local network
and I want my developers to feel the
pain of loading a large page or you know,
whatever it is and or I may want to show,
it was pretty common to show profiling
information on my page in development.
Right and I can see like what is my page
running and loading quickly that
kind of profiling and then when I'm in
production I may want to dial all that down
So, all I love that you showed
all those different ways
and then how I can
use those custom Startup classes to
kind of formalize that.
Yep the last thing
the Visual Studio browser link tool is
enabled by default using that
same mechanism where it checks if its
development mode in the default
application templates
as well. You know that's
one other thing you pointed out, there is
that I can set breakpoints
and I can actually step through and say
like is in development or whatever
that's a neat thing there
is that code is actually
it's code. So I can debug it, I can
you know change their or work with
it as I'm developing. Yep!So thank
so much for joining us for this video
about different environments that you
may be working on. We have a couple more
videos about ASP.NET core for you, I hope
you come back and join us.