Hi I'm Jon Galloway and I'm Jeff Fritz.
So we're digging into ASP.NET Core
and you're going to be showing us ASP.NET Core configuration.
Yeah, what are the
different ways that I can configure my
application, there's so much that I want
to be able to control about how it
starts, how it runs and I want to be able
to access those configuration settings
from different places
in my application.
What are my options there?
What can I do with it? all right.
So let's take a look
here on on my machine, I've got a couple of things already configured I've started with a sample application that it was a ASP.NET application using razor pages
of things already configured I've started with a sample application that it was a ASP.NET application using razor pages
started with a sample application that it was a ASP.NET application using razor pages
and I've got a couple of things written out here that I want to show you,
written out here that I want to show you,
first-off is if I want to actually grab
MyConfiguration and have that strongly
typed configuration class, I can write a
class a normal class it's a plain old
CLR class here and I'm going to provide two
properties inside of this
configuration class.
I'm going to specify my menu bar
background color and then like the text
color that I want to set for my menu bar
in my application. Okay, so this class
it's pretty simple it's using default
property values so that I can set that I
want a black background with white text
and inside of my startup class I can
configure that, based on the
configuration that's available in my
application by using this
services.configure method
inside of my configure services method.
I'm going to configure a MyConfiguration
MyConfiguration class using the section
from MyConfiguration
that's labeled from My-
configuration collection called
MyConfiguration. So right now inside of
my appsettings.JSON I don't have a my
configuration section, so when I run this
application right now
with these settings,
let me just dotnet run that and I will
copy this location and go
over to my browser,
I will go over to Firefox here and let's
paste that in and you'll see that I get
a Configuration
Sample information this
is the stuff that I wrote into the
middle of my page, my header is black
I've got some information being dumped
out on the footer. Now let's take a look
at how I'm getting MyConfiguration
information into this page, let me go
back to my code I'll go over to the
pages and I want to show you the layout.
Now the layout I'm injecting the
configuration object and I'm also going
to inject MyConfiguration options,
so that MyConfiguration
class is actually
being wrapped by an IOptions object
and I can get back my
configuration class
fully populated with whatever
configuration and information it read,
by accessing MyConfigOptions.value
And then to make this demo a little bit
interesting so that you can see how
we're using configuration inside of code
I'm just echoing the menu background
color for my nav bar color and I'm
echoing the text color and making both
of those items important in my CSS here
inside of my layout. Now this could be a
connection string for
your application,
this could be client ID access
information to access a third-party
provider, maybe it's something like a
SendGrid or Twitter, those things can be
configured in your configuration
and used elsewhere in your code by
putting them into a
strongly typed class like this.
The last thing that I want to
show is the environment variables are
being loaded up from my application
and by default, things like the windows
computer name environment variable is
being added to MyConfiguration and I
can see that here in the footer
JEFFS-YOGA that's the name of my machine,
I'm accessing that by using this
indexer to grab that
configuration piece
of information and write it
out to the page.
But now let's let's start changing
things up a little bit, we know that we
read from app settings,
so let's write a section into
app settings for MyConfiguration this
is JSON, so I will add a JSON group here
and we will have MenubarBgcolor
and we will specify, let's start I want to
make the background green and then my
MenubarColor the text color,
let's make it black.
Alright, make sure I put that
comma in there. So now I have properly
formatted app settings,
I'll go over here
and I will restart my application so
that we load up that new configuration
and I'll refresh my page and of course
my header turns green with black text
because now I'm reading settings from
appsettings.JSON .But we actually have
configuration by default inside of our
ASP.NET Core application
that will read-in
appsettings.environmentname.JSON
and we can override whatever's
inside of appsettings, this is the next
step in our configuration hierarchy.
So that's really useful because I can say
like this is my main app settings that
I'm going to be deploying to my server
but when I'm in development I want to
override some of those settings not all
of them but maybe just a few of them.
Maybe just a few, so I'm going to copy out
this MyConfiguration section go over
into my appsettings.Development.json
file this is the default file that we
provide for you when you're building
inside of Visual Studio and I'm going to
change my menu
background color to purple
and let's make this light gray so
that we can still read,
let me restart my application.
And I'll browse to my application now,
and now I get the purple background,
so the configuration for the green with
black text is still there but this one
is loaded second, so this one will
overlay that other configuration. Now I
mentioned things like
Twitter passwords
or connection strings that might be
important to you
we know and we talked a
little bit about putting
those into user secrets,
user secrets are a configuration
option that's loaded next and it should
live in a file that's
outside of our project.
So I'm going to right click on
my project here in Visual Studio and I'm
going to choose Manage User Secrets and I
get an empty .json
file called secrets.json
I'm going to paste in my
configuration here let's change this up
a little bit, this is my secure
information so I will make the
background color red and the
menu bar color white.
I still have my other
configuration settings out there but
I've added user secrets, these will be
loaded if there are user secrets present
and we're in development mode. So now
I'll go back to my page and I'll refresh
and now I get the red with white text,
so I've got three
different configurations
coming in and this is the order in which
they're overriding each other
and changing MyConfiguration.
Okay, so the
difference just to make sure I got it
the difference between the
appsettings.Development
and secrets,
appsettingsDevelopment is
included in the code that I may be
checking into source control that kind
of thing right, yes. And user secrets
that's somewhere else. That's kept
somewhere else on disk, you shouldn't be
checking it into source control, you
don't want folks to be able to see your
passwords and things
inside of source control.
Okay. But in this case just to
illustrate that this is in a different
place I'm just changing the color of the
navigation bar. Great ok.
So the next thing we
already saw that it's loading the
environment variables like my computer
name there in the footer. I can access
and send in environment variables to
overwrite those different settings, so
check this out I might have in my
environment something that will setup
environment variables like
MyConfiguration_MenubarBgColor is
yellow, MenubarColor is
black and these
environment settings are
things that our operations folks can set
up on the server either by having some
sort of a script file like this or maybe
they set it up right in their windows
configuration or in different service
configurations in Linux as the
webservice is starting up.
So I'm going to go
back to my console window here
and I'm going to run
this set environment
command and it's got a couple extra
spaces in there that it's not happy
about, let me just copy these settings in
there we go. Now notice that
configuration setting
is hierarchical, so
how do we define that hierarchy that
we're setting my configuration and then
these items inside of it, you separate
them by using a double underscore
between each one of the pieces of that
configuration key we want to configure.
So I will dotnet run again and this time
with those environment variables in
place I should see a yellow navigation
bar with black text, because it's coming
from my environment variable settings.
Now this is also really powerful on
Azure app service because we have that
console on Azure where you see all the
environment variables that are being
configured specifically for my
application and I can add-in in this
case MyConfiguration_MenubarBgColor
on Azure and set those settings
appropriately. Now there's one
final place I want to show you that you
can add configuration
to override things.
Environment variables is the last thing
in the stack that's being configured
inside of ASP.NET Core. IIS has their own
configuration settings that they will
load up from within web config when my
application is running
inside of IIS. So the
Internet Information Server on Windows
uses something called the ASP.NET Core
module and it has a web config
looks like this
when it runs my application. I can place
inside of here an entry for
environmentVariables
that are specific just to this
process that we're hosting that's
running our Kestrel web server for
ASP.NET core. So I will add an
environmentVariable
and I'm going to use those same
names that I had before
MyConfiguration_MenubarBgColor
and I'll specify the value of that
environmentVariable, let's
make it skyblue,
I'll create one more
environmentVariable,
this is MyConfiguration_MenubarColor
and this time we're going to make
that black, all right. So now if I restart
over here inside of my console window
and I'm going to browse back to my
application, this time I still get the
yellow and black. I get the yellow
and black because I'm running inside of
kestrel not inside of IIS. So let me go
back one more time, I'm going to run this
using IIS Express, so it
reads my web.config
and parses these environmentVariables
for the .Net process that
it's hosting. So I'll launch the IIS Express
instance it's going to use my
web.config that I
wrote, starting my browser
and now I get the sky-blue with black. So
I have written configuration
specifically for the web server to use.
It's being parsed and added in, that
gives you a level of configuration if
you want to do something specific to
IIS only for this process because you
don't want to share
those environment variables
with other processes perhaps
in a shared hosting environment, right.
But we have all these different options
we can work with.
Okay. So to recap we set configuration
for our application from half-dozen
different places where there was
appsettings.json, appsettings with the
environmentname.json in this case
development, but I could also write an
appsetting.staging if I have
configuration information that's
specific to my staging environment that
I want my testers to be able to work
with. I can also have app settings
production.json that my DevOps folks
manage in the upper in the production
space. I can set environment
variables, I can use user secrets to hide
things on just the development machine
and those environmentVariables can be
set specifically for the web server in
the web server process. It's a lot of
flexibility and a lot of options, I've
accessed my configuration on my page
both with an indexer by saying computer
name inside of the configuration object
and but also by creating that my
configuration strongly
typed class that
had properties defined for those things
inside of it, pretty cool stuff.
You know some things
that you showed that I think are really
worthwhile, one is I've got a lot of
flexibility so as I'm developing I can
say this is how I want to work in
production, this is how I want to work
locally and all that. Another thing is it
makes it a lot easier to be secure
and not accidentally
checking my, you know
passwords and secrets into source
control because of things like I can put
locally when I develop, I can put those
in my user secrets and in production say
on Azure I can create those as
environment settings, environment
variables or I can create those you know
and whatever my server is set those up
as environmentVariables it's a much
better you know it kind of pushes you
away from putting those things you don't
want to accidentally share makes it
easier for you to keep them locally in
your environment and in your production
environments as well. It's very
flexible, very powerful you can use those
same things when you start using other
tools like Docker Containers, we can
inject our environmentVariables that
way as well,Great,  cool stuff.
Thanks for joining us
hope you'll stick around for some more
videos on ASP.NET Core.