Hey there, welcome back to this video
about ASP.NET Core, my name is Jeff Fritz,
I'm Jon Galloway. And we've been
talking a lot in these videos about
building new applications and what we
can do with them and then we even got
into talking a little bit about
production and different environments.
How do I host this? This stuff if I want to
actually publish it and put it
somewhere in a production space Jon.
Yeah, it's a great question and it's--
there's a lot of information,
a lot of it like nuances to this right
deploying has gotten a
little more complicated because
ASP.NET Core runs everywhere
yeah, so you have to think about
you know how is
your application actually hosted
and how are-- you know
where are you deploying it to
and the slight differences
between the places you can deploy it to.
OK. So to start with
we're going to talk about
actually hosting in ASP.NET Core
and you know
an interesting thing here is that
ASP.NET Core is actually
hosted using Kestrel.
OK, And Kestrel is a
lightweight Web Server package,
it's actually a NuGet package
that I add to my application
that kind of turns on HTTP serving.
OK, so I manage HTTP server
that lives inside of my application.
So, the kind of the common things
to any environment is
you'll set up a host and then once you
you will publish, you know
your application to a folder on there,
you'll set-- you'll have a process manager
that's going to make sure that
my application continues running.
OK. And then I'm going to have a
reverse proxy that's going to send the
traffic back to me. OK.
So that whole thing about you know,
how I'm actually publishing and I'm how my
application is hosting itself
is, this is done using Kestrel
so to see this in action let's take a look at
a default project
this is just File, New Project. OK.
And I've got-- if I look in my
NuGet packages,
I've got the AspNetCoreAll meta package.
Sure. And if I expand this out
somewhere in that list
we've got Kestrel, so if I--
So, you actually don't need to install
kestrel in your application
File, New web is going to have
Kestrel enabled by default. Right,
because that package is
included as part of that
AspNetCore.All meta package that has
everything in the kitchen-sink. Yep,
and I could actually
just create a console application
and then add this Kestrel package
and my application is now
a web app. Oh! cool. Right,
so that's pretty neat.
So if we-- if we hop back out of there
and we look at our Startup,
so excuse me our program CS.
What we've got here is
the actual spinning up Kestrel
and you mentioned, if you could
start a console application
and add the web server to it
this looks like a normal
static void main for a console application.
It completely is-- oh!
No trickery at all this is literally
a console app that has some additional
NuGet packages added
and because of that
we've got Microsoft ASPNetCore Hosting
and that's able to run Kestrel and host
our application. Cool!
So, in previous releases
before Asp.NetCore2,
there was a lot more code in here.
And it was pretty much boilerplate
you always did the same things
you always said here use--
you know, use these environment settings
and do this and do that.
So what they've done and I like this
it's definitely simplified things
quite a bit for me is
they've got a default web host builder
you'll see here
a WebHost CreateDefaultBuilder
and for the most part I can just
use this and go on about my merry way.
If I do want to go in and configure things,
I can you know just type dot
and then I can start
you know I can go in here
and I can configure specifics about
how things work. But for the most part
I can start with this default
WebHostBuilder and I'm pretty sad.
Cool! If I do want to
dig into what else is available in the
GitHub AspNet Hosting repo, there's a
sample which has some additional hosting
configurations. So, here's one
where they show
for instance if I want to point
other URLs if I want to say, I want my
application to respond to you know,
5000 and 5001 or you know
if I want to respond
only to this on HTTPs or other things.
This is an example of
how I could go in and do that
so I'm just dotting in and adding
and making additional calls
to the WebHostBuilder. Cool!
And for an example, taking this even further
this is one where there-- it's a sample
where it's doing all kinds of
additional configuration adding
in specific configuration steps,
we're doing things like
using a specific ContentRoot
so this the ContentRoot is
where my www Root folder
points to-- OK.
And I could point this somewhere else,
right? Here we're doing
some additional UseUrls
one for HTTP and one for HTTPS.
You can encode, you
could set a different
development environment, you know
just all kinds of different things.
So here we're configuring services
in line here. Your services are
normally configured
in a Startup class, but if you look at it
if we go back over to it in here
this when this calls
use Startup, that's actually
just a convention for like a nice way to
clean up my program CS, so all the code
isn't in there, right? So I really could
configure inline here if I had to need to.
So this is an example of doing
that sort of thing. So, here in this
example they're using a fake server
and that's just for testing, you know
they're running a local one, there's
other options
there's things like this HttpSys server.
Right, so that's built on top of the
Http.Sys kernel mode driver
inside of Windows that will serve
web interactions, web--
web concerns from there,
very cool to give you all the power of
Windows web serving
using a new server that's built
with .NET completely managed
and running here inside of your
AspNetCore app.
Cool! So to summarize
what we've covered so far, we've got a
NuGet package called Kestrel, we are
pulling it into our application
which really was just a console app
and then we said pull in this
NuGet package
and then configure it and now
my console application is a web server.
Pretty cool!
pretty neat! So now that we've got
that, we can look at
where are we going to deploy this to.
And as I mentioned before there's--
those steps to it, so number one we've got our
host setup then there are other things
that you know, now we want to
get this out on to them and run them.
So, we publish to a folder
and you know if I right click
publish in Visual Studio
or if I publish using that
like the Azure tools etc, a lot of those
things are kind of handled for me but
all I need to do from command line is
type dotnet publish and that's going to
publish just the code
that I'm going to want to deploy.
Alright. So after that
there's kind of different steps for the
different environments as far as
how my process is monitored?
And what the reverse proxy is,
how it's actually how, what the
web server is it's kind of feeding
things into Kestrel. Right, so that
reverse proxy is a front-end
commercial-grade web server
like Apache, Nginx or IIS
that's going to receive
those initial requests, maybe it'll
handle those SSL interactions
any kind of other security concerns
and then turn around
and submit that request back
to Kestrel much the same way that folks in--
in the node environment use Express.
Exactly and then you know, my application
is concerned with just serving HTTP
and all those kind of other higher-level
things that I may want to do and you know
like you said a commercial-grade
web server I can handle that stuff there.
So as we kind of go through some of the
different options for deploying.
So IIS, there's actually
this is a long article
here about setting up IIS and there are
a decent amount of steps to this which is
one reason honestly, that I like
deploy into Azure because I can just
push at Azure and let them
worry about that. Let them
configure for you and they take all those
predefined defaults the
best practices for you. Yep!
And handle things like you know,
Windows Update, yes.
But so these are kind of the examples
here this is walking through me
through setting up IIS.
There is an ASP NET Core,
so there's a-- what is it .NET Core
Windows Server Hosting bundle
and this is an exe.
This is something that I would install
on my server my web server and it'll
actually go through
and configure things for me.
So if you were setting up a VM in
Azure or if you had an on-prem server
that you were configuring IIS on to also
have .NET Core hosting you would use
this .NET Core Windows Server
Hosting bundle.
to put down those features from
ASP.NET Core we need in
order to host a website.
Exactly! So the way this is done
in IIS after I've installed that is it's
actually using this ASP.NET Core module.
And the ASP NET Core module is actually
doing this proxy for me. So if we look at it
here's the internet IIS is that
front end and it's actually got this
core module that it's running and that
core module is calling back into my
application. And then as we see here,
here's my application and it's actually
got Kestrel as kind of the front end
that's calling back and forth into my
application code. Cool! So yeah, so this is
really interesting and of course this is
like I said this is installed by that
server install thing for me.
So that will kind of
set it up for me with IIS.
So that that's how it's done there
and that's kind of the main way that you're
going to be doing this. There are
some other options available though.
There's the option to
host in a Windows service
which is pretty neat. So there's actually
a package that I'm-- I'm able to install
that can set that up. This is the
Microsoft.AspNet.Core.Hosting.WindowsServices
package and so if I add that
into my application here, so you'll
see this is-- this is you know, got that
pulled in and then it's actually pretty
similar on start. There's a few things,
we're doing here we're saying the
very simplest case is you
basically run it
and it's-- it's configured as a service.
However, a lot of the time
I want to actually be
able to debug it and build you know like
I want as I'm-- as I'm developing my
application I want to be able to kind of
step into the code debug and all that
kind of stuff. So kind of the recommended
way and this is shown in the docs is to
set it up where you can say allow it to
run in dual mode either as a console app
or as a service. OK. So the way this is
configured here this is saying if it's
if a debugger is attached or if I pass
in the command line arguments
--console then set this is service to false.
And then it runs slightly differently
if it says it's, if it is a
service then it kind of sets--
sets things for a directory path
the directory path is different
right and then also there's
this host.RunAsCustomService so
this is what's pulled in
via that NuGet package.
So this is the standard kestrel run
but if we're running if as service
then it does this run as custom service.
OK. And then the way
that's registered is actually
using this SC command. So if we take
a look I've actually got this here,
jump over into folder and I set this up
using a batch file and only because
this is a few lines of code to type here.
So if we look, so this is sc create
so that's sc is the-- the thing to kind of
register a service, so I say sc create
the name of the service and then binPath.
And the one thing that's-- that's a
little interesting this binPath
I've actually used .net publish
So in my application I--
from command-line I did
.net publish and I-- and then I've copied
that path where the exe was published to.
OK. So now I'm going to take this service
and I will do run as administrator
And that's now running that's like
that was it's registered as a service
and so now if I go to localhost 5,000,
my favorite localhost port.
So there's my service running this is
being hosted as a
service a Windows Service.
So the Windows Service is handling
the you know, keeping my process
running handling the
Start/Stop all that kind of stuff.
So this is a lot like how we would
do those self-contained deployments
with WCF services, back in the past.
Yep! Exactly!
So again if I'm exposing something out on
the internet I would generally expose
I would use IIS, right.
Sure, but for something
that I need to host locally have a
service that's running exposed some
local content et cetera that's-- that's
kind of how I can set that up.
So yeah and that's-- that sample is out that's
actually linked to from the docs here.
OK. So relatively straightforward
and that sc I was honestly
kind of surprised when I
you know, did the sc running
through this sc service add and it just
kind of worked sc create so
and then at the end also
you'll want to go through
and clean it up, remove it
and that's there's an sc delete
To do that you stop it and delete it.
So that is those, so the
one other thing I kind of wanted to
touch on and this is a bigger you know,
thing I'm just going to point you
in the direction to get started
but is hosting on Linux.
Hosting on Linux again, you're
configuring an entire web server you're
setting up your process monitor
and you're doing your reverse proxy.
OK. So there's several steps there,
I just want to point out
I ran through this and I just
want to point out some got to
and important things to be aware of right.
And also some tips, so one has I went in
and actually did this in the-- I created
an Ubuntu VM and I did--
I did my kind of development
on that machine as far as
kind of configuring it actually use the
Cloud Shell. So this Cloud Shell you-- you
can just bring up by clicking here.
And this kind of launches, this little
terminal window down at the bottom.
OK. So that's actually where I did
my configuration in order to do
that I-- I ssh into the box. OK.
So I actually just you know, copy I
it's in the-- in the directions as far as
how to do it but I ssh into the box
and then they walk you
through installing.
Now you can install the full SDK
but actually what's recommended
is to install just the runtime.
Sure, or you don't want
to install the whole SDK on
your server though you don't need it.
And-- and you want to
kind of have a light-tight
install right. So when you go to the
downloads and kind of the default it's
going to point you to is SDK.
If you click on runtime then you can
scroll down and you can see here Linux
installing .NET Core on Linux.
And then here
be careful that you read the
Version Number. So this is .NET core 1.1.4 (LTS).
It's long term support right.
So, you actually do if you want .NET Core 2
you want to scroll down to current.
And then for these it's-- it's literally just
sudo apt-get you know, you have to
configure the sources for it first.
So those sources are these
standard ones here.
So, if you go downloads .NET Core
and then you click on Linux.
You're still going to need to
make sure that
for whatever your environment is that
you've done your apt-get.
You know to you like you've
configured your sources for apt-get
Right! So I went through and then you know,
registered the Microsoft Signature
you know go through
and then install-- install
the apt-get using this.
However, when I got to this line here
where-- where you would run the entire SDK
that's where instead you
install that runtime. OK.
That makes sense. Yeah! So that's--
that's kind of the main thing
as far as how you deploy.
Obviously, you know I recommend
still deploying using
continuous integration
using some sort of like
deploy from GitHub or that kind of
thing that's kind of nice
to configure that.
When you're in development
one nice thing that you can do
if you're developing on Windows you can
actually use Bash Ubuntu on Windows.
So, I went through and you know
locally did this on my machine
you know .NET and I actually have .NET cd
and so I did through here .NET publish,
so it's-- it's in a sub-directory
off a bin, cd bin
debug and then down underneath
its several levels but there's
a published directory right.
And then as far as how you get your
files out on your production server
what I did locally in development
is use scp.
There's information in the docs
about how to do that?
and so basically rp is recursive
I saw I'm pointing to
a directory I'm saying scp
from this local directory
to my-- my azure VM's directory.
And I just created an app directory
and did you know scp
just copy to that. Yeah, that's kind
of a standard you know,
way to deploy or to copy files up.
So, once I had that in place then that's
my applications are running
on that server. OK.
So then to actually run it start and hit
you know and then just the DLL name. Right!
After that though you're not done
because remember you've got to go through,
and do all the actual
hosting steps in here so,
you're actually just your application
has copied up there but now
you've got to have
your monitoring and you also need
to handle your reverse proxy.
So we're not going to go through
all that now I'm just
showing you kind of the basics of how to
get started and how to get it.
You know get it running and can
and important considerations
you've got. Sure, ok.
So we have covered
starting with the basics of
how your application is hosted itself.
How kestrel is running
your application or is
enabling HTTP serving inside
your application, right?
And we looked at how you configure that,
how you can set up some of the
different kestrel options?
You've got your default web host builder
to start with but you can go through
and configure a lot of different things
and we looked at some sample code for that.
After that we looked at how
we're deploying to a few different
hosting environments so we looked at IIS,
We looked at hosting locally
as a Window Servers,
we looked at some kind
of things to be aware of for
deploying to Ubuntu as well. Cool!
Alright! We covered a lot there,
I learned a lot about
hosting an ASP.NET Core Servers.
Thanks so much for joining us.
I hope you follow up with
some of the other videos
that we have in our
ASP.NET Core Series for you.